this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello everyone welcome to
Sulphur engineering radio my name is
Polina and today with me on the show I
have Mike McCourt's Mike is a data
scientist but before he was he was an
astrophysicist he actually has a PhD in
physics he had worked a different
University in the United States where he
studied galaxies formations but he now
works at a cool analytics company called
invoke I where he designs machine
learning models to help businesses
categorize and understand their incoming
phone calls
welcome to the show Mike thanks so much
for having me here so the topic of the
show today is analyzing voice Dana and
as you might know voice data really is
everywhere like I have an Alexa at home
and an Apple watch talking to computers
is actually not a thing of the future
anymore many people do it now but I
don't even really know how it works Mike
could you take us through the basic
steps of how an Apple watch knows the
routes to the nearest bus station yeah
that's a great question so the way that
speech recognition worse has actually
changed quite a bit in the last few
years there's the traditional type of
model that it's a statistical model
called a hidden Markov model recently
there's been a move towards using deep
neural network to do speech reading
recognition I think the the hidden
Markov model is is the easier one to
discuss but there are a number of steps
and the key idea is that words are not
the fundamental element of speech words
are actually made up of smaller
components I think they're called
phonemes or phonemes I'm not sure in the
pronunciation but the key idea is that
you know in the English language at
least we have millions of words but
they're made up of a much smaller number
of phonemes a few dozen and so the first
step in speech recognition
is to break up the audio stream into
these phonons these building blocks of
words and I suppose the first step that
you need to know in order to do that is
some linguistic knowledge how long does
a phoneme actually last here's an
example maybe of what a phoneme is
because I guess if people have never
heard of it it's a little bit abstract
what exactly is a phony unfortunately
I'm not a linguist so I may not give the
best answer they're sort of like letters
so like the word cat I think has three
phonemes the cat and the tongue those
are the building blocks that make up
that word but they're they're not
exactly letters I think English has 40 I
think you told me there were 44 phonemes
in English and obviously 26 letters but
they're they're roughly that building
blocks of words yeah sometimes I think
also they can be two letters like the P
and H together are the F sounds in some
cases and that would be one phoneme
because there's one sound Eli I'm also
not a linguist but I think it's more or
less the easy thing is like if it's one
sound then is more or less one phonemes
if they're linguists in the audience
we're sorry for butchering your area of
expertise yeah my training is in physics
yes I think I think the first step that
you really need to know is well how long
does a phoneme blast if you're gonna
divide up the audio stream into these
phonemes you need you need to be looking
on the right time scale and so as the
audio stream comes in you chunk it out
into segments that are overlapping and
then you want each segment to be short
enough that it probably has just one
phone a minute but long enough that you
can actually capture the acoustic
signature of those onions okay so step
one is we have raw audio that you type
you could you speak into your phone or
your Alexa or in the phone call in your
example really over the phone mm-hm and
then you divide that into phonemes and
then what is the next step well
unfortunately you don't know the
phonemes yet so you divide it into
segments of time but then you still have
to figure out you have to turn that
audio into the phoneme and so there's a
transformation you do in in physics we
call it a form you transform but it
decomposes audio into the frequencies
that make up that audio and so if you
were to do this on a piece of music it
would tell you what notes made up that
music human speech is not quite made up
of musical notes but it's a similar idea
and then that gives you a acoustic
signature for that small time window and
then that that is a signature that you
try to match against library Estonians
you have ah I see so first you're trying
to guess which piece of audio could more
or less realistically represent a
phoneme in terms of the length of the
audio and then you match that piece
against a known database of all those
the smaller set of phonemes that exists
in English exactly yeah so then what
happens if word sounds really the same
like 8 the number and 8 as in I had
something for dinner for me that sounds
exactly the same
yeah how do you distinguish words with
exactly the same sounds yeah so there's
still two more steps so you can take the
audio stream you break it up into these
these signatures of frequencies you
match those against phonemes and then
from the phonemes you need to get to a
word any use a pronounciation dictionary
for that but but like you said that the
same set of phonemes could be multiple
different words and so on top of that
you have a language model so you know 8
the number or 8 the verb those sound the
same but the words that come before or
after can give you an indication of
which one was the intention of the
speaker and so you have a statistical
mapping from the audio to the phoneme
and that that's never going to be
certain because different people speak
differently they have different accents
they might be using they might have a
bad audio connection and so on so that's
a statistical connection and then the
mapping of the pronunciation to words
is also a statistical the
might be different ways to pronounce the
word and then which word choice is
statistical because some words sound the
same and you have to determine from
context what the most likely outcome is
and so you have these three
probabilistic connections and at the end
of the day you multiply those
probabilities probabilities together and
you hope that the probability peaks at a
particular word and then there's a level
of the matching only the word or the
phoneme or does it also take the context
of the whole sentence or maybe even the
whole conversation into account yeah so
now that last bit like you said
distinguishing between eight the number
and eight the verb that that's taking
context into account ideally you'd want
to take the whole conversation as
context because that would that's useful
information and you could use that to
really really nail down the
probabilities but that becomes too
computationally expensive so typically
you use a handful of words preceding
that may be four or five words as
context okay so it would be feasible and
it might be better to take a bigger
context into account like a preview
sentence or another call from the same
person but just because that's too
expensive you only look ahead or you
only look back a few words exactly yeah
if only they gave us bigger computers so
talking about taking context into
account what about actions like as
people know I'm not a native speaker of
English and this is probably here both
for people is this also a year before
algorithms like if I if my species
processed does my Alexa know oh that's
the Dutch lady again we have to process
or slightly differently they do so it
depends a little bit on on how the model
is implemented so in all those steps
that we laid out there's there's
actually tremendous freedom in how you
design an algorithm to do that typically
because speech recognition has to be
done really quickly the the algorithm
for matching that acoustic signature to
a phoneme
it's often a relatively simple one
people just use a normal distribution
and hope that that works a normal
distribution might work really well if
everyone had the same
or if you were designing speech
recognition for just one person but if
you have different accents or different
people speaking people with different
pitches in their voice or someone's
typically they're using the same
phonemes to make up a word they just the
phonemes sounds a little bit differently
when they say that and so that
complicates the relationship between the
that acoustic signature and the phoneme
that mapping and so you have a choice in
how you do the algorithm you can
implement a latent variable which will
actually try to figure out the absent of
the speaker and their pitch and and
other characteristics of their voice and
tune to that or you can design an
algorithm that just tries to fit
everyone and that that mapping is made
complicated enough you know the tent is
big enough so that that everyone can fit
inside of it and which one would be a
more successful approach is it is better
if you have a sense of what someone's
accent is to classify that always in a
certain case or is it better to just be
very flexible and are able to analyze
all sorts of different accents at the
same time you know I don't know I
suspect I suspect that for performance
reasons most companies do the latter
they adopt a flexible model that that
can try to work for everyone they might
see better performance if that were
tuned with the latent variable yeah that
if it's more precise if it's zooming in
more on your personal characteristics it
would be better but maybe it's not it's
not feasible for performance reasons
yeah well and I think there's a trade
enough you know if the if the flexible
model works well enough then it may not
be worth paying a performance penalty to
now yeah and what about other languages
because Dutch is still sort of similar
to English in the sense that we only
indicate meaning with words but a
language like Chinese
they're also tone matters for meaning if
you end a word in a certain higher pitch
or a lower pitch then the meaning might
be different is that a thing that's
taken into account from the beginning of
the algorithm or though you just still
do the first phony matching steps and
then in the statistical analysis you
didn't take
into account the different pictures and
tones in for example Chinese yeah I have
to know almost nothing about Chinese so
I don't I don't know if the sinem notion
of a phoneme works for Chinese I suspect
there's something analogous and that the
same type of algorithm to work I was
actually trying to think of an example
in English where Tull and your stress
could matter and the only example I came
up with is the word invite so if in
American English at least if you say
invite you we hear that as a verb
you know I'm inviting you to something
but now Americans will also say I sent
you an invite and if you stress the
first the first syllable of that word we
hear that as a noun so that's an example
where something other than the phoneme
in this case the stress on the syllable
actually matters for the meaning that
that was the only example I can think of
in English and fortunately for
speech-to-text algorithms invite as I
now in an invite as a verb respond the
same
so you'll never know if the algorithms
got that right yeah I know there's
actually there's a paper about whether
or not words are stressed and the
scientific paper in the title of the
paper is stress matters revisited so you
can and as stress matters revisited are
you clever and interesting that matters
yeah so there must be more examples of
where stress matters but its way is way
different still them for Chinese but
sadly enough you don't know all the
details with that so let's move on to
the topic of white voice analysis is
hard why do we have a whole episode of
software engineering rodeo radio
dedicated to this topic so what are some
of the issues that you run into when
you're analyzing voice data you're
trying to make it into textual data for
further processing so fortunately for me
I don't actually do the voice to test
part I'm the consumer at this technology
not a producer of that aspect but I
think the key reason that it's hard is
you know as we said there are three
different steps you have to go through
to turn the audio into
a word and they're all probabilistic and
so you never know what the right answer
is and you have to compute many
different possibilities and if you're if
you're using context over five words you
have to keep track of you know a huge
number of different possibilities and
solve for the probabilities of each and
then at the end you figure out what your
best answer is going to be so it's a
it's computationally intensive and it's
hard to keep track of all those
different possibilities and these
different possibilities probably exist
at different levels right so people are
different but also other aspects of how
people speak might impact this analysis
like if people are angry or if they're
stressed then that is an extra dimension
of speech differences is that second aim
to account is that even that might be
more interesting and more closer to what
you are doing do you still get the
emotion from the voice in a textual
description so if you get the output of
the algorithm does it say set in an
angry voice nah not the output that I
get although that would be interesting
to play with yeah yeah you know what I
found
this often comes up on my team and we're
like God wouldn't it be so great if we
could get the volume of the voice or the
intonation Wow was an infant thing won
also yeah you know so far what we found
is that language is incredibly rich and
the words that you use convey a huge
amount of meaning and we're still not
tapping all of that meeting and so we
we've not yet felt the need to go into
looking at the folly of and stress and
intonation we still have a huge amount
of information that we're sitting on
that word we're trying to utilize more
efficiently yeah Leah let's zoom into
the topic of would you actually do with
voice analysis so as far as I understand
the work that you do is you try to help
companies classify calls that people
make to their company and also the
classification is done automatically
with machine learning models could you
share a little bit more about your use
case and
technology's involved in the u.s. gays
yeah so we do call analytics for
marketing and in today's world marketers
are used to getting a lot of information
about purchases that happen online and
so if you're reading the newspaper and
you see an ad for something click on the
ad go to a website and buy something
they know exactly what ad drove that
purchase and they know that they can
invest more of their energy into that
advertising campaign and that that's
become hugely important in the internet
economy today they lose a lot of that
information when you pick up the phone
and so if you see an ad but you don't
click on it and buy the line you instead
call the company and make a purchase
they don't know necessarily what ad
drove out and so they don't know how to
maximize their optimize their
advertising campaigns so we work to do
that to provide attribution for
purchases that happen over the phone and
then the the team that I work on we try
to analyze what actually took place on
the phone so that you're not optimizing
merely ad campaigns that drove more
calls but you're optimizing for ad
campaigns it drove calls for people who
actually purchased something so could
you give a concrete example of some of
that analysis I find it hard to really
to understand in a concrete sense what
actually could you give an example of a
phone call that you analyzed and the
steps to consequences a company took
based on the analysis yeah so a real a
really typical use case for us would be
either purchase or an appointment so
let's take the example of an appointment
if you're let's say a dentist's office
in Santa Barbara where I work you might
put out advertisements and a couple
different newspapers you've opened a new
dental office and you're looking for
patients and you know you might put in
put an ad in the New York Times which
has a huge readership all the way across
the United States and you might put an
ad in a local Santa Barbara newspaper
and that has a much smaller readership
but they're people who are nearby and
you know if you track
many people are calling in from each
advertisement you might be getting many
more calls from the New York Times out
because it has a bigger readership but
since those people are less likely to be
in Santa Barbara they're less likely to
actually make an appointment and what
our software can do there the software
that I work on can do is that it can
analyze those calls and tell you whether
implants made and you might find that
even though the Santa Barbara newspaper
is driving fewer calls those people are
more likely to make an appointment and
so based on that information the dental
office might might realize that they
should move some of their advertising
money away from the New York Times and
towards the local newspaper so that's
the goal of what we do yes some of the
goals might be you listen to a call and
you want to automatically detect was
this a call in which an appointment was
made or was this a call in which
purchase was made so that you can then
detect the source of an ad and the
sources of then a phone call is it more
likely to truly to an ad or a purchase
or an appointment exactly yeah we're
helping business is optimized and how
far does this go is it just a purchase
was made or ain't an appointment was
made or is it also an appointment was
made for I know a specific dental
procedure that is more expensive and
gaining more profits for the dentist you
zoom in into the visuals of such phone
call so that that's actually why
analyzing phone calls is really tricky
is you you quickly learn that there
isn't just one type of appointment there
could be a first-time patient who has to
be enrolled and they have to give a
whole lot of their their information to
get into the system at the office it
could be a returning patient who's
already in the system and it's a very
short phone call to schedule an
appointment you know a kid in a dental
office it could be someone who's having
an emergency they're in pain and they
want to get an appointment right away
so you quickly learn that there is no
one type of conversation people are so
different that you know no two people
who call in there are going to have the
same conversation yeah I guess that's
what makes your work so interesting
because if it was all literally the same
conversation then there
no analysis would be needed so could you
talk more about how that analysis worked
works is this a supervised machine
learning motorway you have already
access to lots of audio that has been
classified by people or is this just
clustering based on similarity and no
labeling is involved so we use a
combination of supervised and
unsupervised techniques so at the end of
the day we're looking for something
that's important to the business and so
they they need to provide examples of
exactly what it is that they're looking
for so you know typically they might
give us a hundred examples of a call
that's what they're looking for and a
hundred examples of calls that don't
reflect that so for the dental office
they make it 100 appointments in 100
calls they're not equipments if we were
to just train and supervise diagur them
on that we would really struggle because
those hundred calls that were
appointments none of them would be alike
and 100 calls that were in on
and you know there there might be some
differences between the groups that we
could detect but they it's pretty hard
to do because different people's wording
is is so distinct and you know in a
typical data set we have there might be
there might be forty thousand words that
appear in the vocabulary just because
different people phrase things
differently and they have their
individual voices so with a hundred
examples trying to learn the importance
of forty thousand words there's just not
enough data to do that so we use a
combination of unsupervised learning and
a supervised cell rhythm and the key
idea that we work with is that you know
no two calls are going to be the same
because people have their individual
voices and their own accents and
dialects and their own personal needs so
they're not going to use the same
sequences of words but there are common
themes that are shared and that run
through the data set and so we try to
build a model that can find these common
themes and we do that by imposing layers
of hierarchy and so we say that on you
know
every individual call their totally
distinct and their totally unique and
that's fine that's great but we're
looking for something that's shared and
you know one thing that we know has to
be shared if if they're all speaking in
England sure if they're all speak
speaking Dutch you know there has to be
a dictionary of words they're using and
if they're speaking language they have
to be using the words from that language
so that that's something that we know is
is shared and we anchor the model on
that and so now we have something that's
like too specific and too unique where
there's too much information to be
useful and then we have something on the
other end where it's too general to be
useful the other end that you have
there's two general is just the two data
sets of appointments and no appointment
that's too general and then just to
summarize what you're saying and then to
specific it here's the words that they
use and then you need to stop you need
something that's in the middle of those
two extremes is that a good summary yeah
to general is the dictionary right I
mean it's very basic right you're using
words from a particular language and
then and then we introduce layers of
specialization so we say okay well then
when you're making a call to a business
you're not going to use every word in
the dictionary there's there's only a
small subset of those words that you use
and and some words are more common than
others but the words that you use depend
on the type of business that you're
calling and so there's a specialization
of that dictionary and that sort of now
reflects an average phone call and then
we say well you know there's not just
one type of phone call there are many
different types of phone calls and so we
model multiple specializations of that
and and those kind of reflect the topics
or the themes the things that people
talk about and then search mode would
always be specific for a certain
customer or a certain domain because the
calls to a dentists are so different
than the goals to I don't know a shoe
shop that those models always have to be
tailored specifically towards a customer
or other parts of the model that you
could always use for any sort sort of
domain yeah I think that's what's really
cool about this approach where we lay
out these levels of specialization
because it allows us to fit different
types of data
in a way where we say you know these are
related but they're not the same and so
a shoe shop would have an appointment
and dentist's office would have an
appointment and those are totally
different and the types of conversations
that you would have might be totally
different but there is actually a lot in
common between them they are speaking
English that's huge that the patterns of
words that are associated just with
having a conversation about scheduling a
time would be shared and so the this
modeling approach that we take with
these levels of specializations that
allows us to fit different types of data
at the same time and borrow what's
common among them but still allow them
to be different yeah so it's partly
supervised that partly unsupervised and
partly domain-specific and partly also
domain independence and Jenny in there
yeah yeah so the the unsupervised part
is what allows us to extract these
common themes and then and then we use
those to do the supervised learning
we're not trying to infer for all 40,000
words in the language what matters for
an appointment we're saying okay there
were like 25 different themes that
occurred on calls to this business which
of those correlate with appointments and
then and then we can use that to make
predictions and that works much better
so what do you exactly do with the
predictions so now you have a prediction
is this live feedback to people who are
on the phone with people that are making
an appointment is it like oh this person
is almost gonna make an appointment
quickly use is this only Meade meant s
feedback about calls that have already
happens to train marketeers to do better
or is this like a feedback yeah that's
that's a conversation that we've had a
number of times and I think it would be
really fun to try to develop that you
know live feedback to the people on the
phone I'm a little skeptical that we can
tell them something that they don't
already know you know a human is a human
having a conversation is very good at
figuring out what's going on or at least
they sufficiently if they work on
on the phonelines so for the for the
moment the bane application that we use
our software for is actually feedback to
the marketers and so that they know
which advertising campaigns they're
running are driving the most business
isn't even at the individual customer
level it isn't at to an agent like this
goal that we had well are our
predictions showed it should have been
an appointment but you didn't get an
appointment so you did something wrong
it's way way more high level than that
where you just want to understand what
type of calls lead to appointments
because that might be good ads or good
sources of people of customers exactly
and and you know a lot of the companies
that are our customers they can owe
thousands and thousands of phone calls a
day and so it would be very difficult
for them to listen to phone calls and
understand what's happening so that they
need a machine learning service like we
have to code through all of that data
and then they get that feedback in real
time when the calls and so that can be
plugged into you know bidding algorithms
for google ads or keywords or however
they choose to render their marketing
campaigns so we talked a little bit
already about why voice analytics is
hard in general but what is specifically
hard about analyzing phone calls because
of course that's not the same as me
talking into my phone to Siri or to
Alexa but I'm calling on the phone what
our specific issues in that situation
yeah that's something that we've really
struggled with a lot of the models sort
of off-the-shelf models that you can use
for analyzing text they're designed for
well traditionally they've been designed
for very clean datasets like New York
Times articles or Wikipedia articles
these are relatively long pieces of text
that has been edited and nicely written
and they're coherent and they have a
point conversation is not always like
that over the course of the phone call
they're figuring out why they called
conversations can kind of jump from one
topic to the next and you know also on
phone calls you have a mixture of
natural conversation that's spontaneous
and unpredictable and that's why we have
to go through all this effort to
introduce these layers of hierarchy to
look for common themes throughout the
conversation but you also have
recordings you know sometimes you're
sitting on hold and it's playing
essentially an advertisement on the hold
message and there's no spontaneity there
that's the same from one called the next
and then sometimes you have an agent
who's reading a script you know if
you're scheduling an appointment at a
dental office again you know they have a
series of questions that they ask they
might be reading that and so you have
these different levels of spontaneity in
the conversations that make it quite
tricky to make a model yeah I was gonna
ask so is a first step trying to
distinguish is this someone reading a
script is this informal chatty like
conversation is that a first step to
divide something into distinct buckets
or is it more a spectrum of this is more
towards formal and this is more towards
loose yeah it would be great if we could
do that as the first step because I
would really like to ignore all of the
scripted stuff in all of the recordings
unfortunately we were not able to tell
based on the words that are spoken we're
not able to tell what type of
conversation it is until we've done our
analysis and so you know the way that
our code works where we're looking we're
looking for these common themes
throughout the data set but we recognize
that every call might be distinct
we have information for each of those
themes we have information on how
similar it is from one call to the next
that's part of the calculation we do to
infer these things and so you know as
words come in and we're trying to figure
out what themes they belong to we can
figure we can say oh this looks like
it's one of those themes that's the same
on every call that's probably a
recording or this looks a lot like an
appointment but all of the words that
are interesting or spoken on the agent
site and so maybe the agents trying to
get someone to make an appointment
they're not doing it Oh question would
be like hey you want an appointment are
you really not interested in appointment
so then it's very much about appointment
but also it isn't because nothing
gonna happen exactly and in some
industries that agents really try to
upsell on the phone and so there's a lot
of conversation you know if you just if
you didn't know who is speaking you'd be
like wow they're buying everything but
it's not it's just the excuse me the
agent is pitching you know many
different products uh so I'm only
realizing now that and also part of the
trickiness of analyzing phone calls
different from analyzing chatting to
Alexa is also determining who is
speaking is it sometimes the case that
the voice of someone that's calling and
the voice of the agents are very similar
and those that lead to problems or is it
very easy to distinguish because you
have different audio tracks like
different files from different sources
so most of the time it's easy for us
because phone data comes in in stereo
and the caller's on one side and the
agents on the other side so that that's
easy for us to distinguish occasionally
we we have mono data and then it's very
hard to tell the speaker's apart yeah
that's another step of all the things
you are already trying to distinguish
from each other yeah so what about audio
quality I can imagine that if I speak
into my phone and I'm not calling or if
I'm speaking to my Alexa in my home that
the call quality of the voice quality is
sort of similar but calling on the phone
if someone that maybe has a really old
phone or really bad connection is this
something that interferes with your
model and how does how do you deal with
that yeah you know unfortunately over
the phone
you have a huge range of call qualities
some are going to be excellent and
crystal-clear and you can hear every
word and the speech-to-text works great
and the the transcript makes perfect
sense
and sometimes you have someone you know
calling on their cell phone from the car
on the freeway and there's static and
the audio quality is horrible and you
know the speech-to-text does the best
that it can but you end up with a
transcript that's relatively garbled
yeah and you know what one of the
challenges and analyzing phone calls is
you need a model that can handle both
cases so you know if your if your model
is really sensitive to patterns so that
even in a really noisy
transcript of that audio quality still
picked out the relevant patterns if you
make your model too sensitive then on a
really good phone call it might falsely
trigger on on words that maybe were set
but don't indicate that you're making it
up my mentor wow that is interesting so
better isn't always better because
better could also be too sensitive and
then also things growing so there's
there's like a sweet spot in the middle
of sensitive enough but not too
sensitive yeah and if the calls were a
consistent quality then it would be easy
to pick how sensitive to make it ya know
calibration and then it would be okay
exactly but you know they keep us on our
feet so there they're different levels
of sensitivity that we need to adapt
based on audio ecology so you already
mentioned some things that could go
wrong like you pick up words but they're
on the agent sites or you have too
sensitive or too little sensitive models
what are other examples of stuff that
makes your work really hard
where do your algorithms get into
trouble yeah and another thing that
sounds simple but that was actually
really a struggle for us is that calls
vary widely in length so some calls are
you know two hours long and Wow
yeah and I've been there before trying
to return something to a business and
you can transfer it many different times
and it takes a while to to get to the
right person and and you know some calls
might just be a minute
you know if you're if you're making an
appointment a dental office again where
you're already a patient you know they
just look you up in the system and they
said great can you come in on Thursday
you said yes and you have an appointment
so there's a huge range in length of
phone calls and again there's a
sensitivity issue where if a phone call
is just a minute long there may be only
a few dozen words spoken and you don't
have a whole lot of evidence to base
your prediction button and so you know
you're you're working on just a handful
of words that might be indicating that
an appointment was made but if you're if
you have a model that will predict on
just a handful of words well in that
hour-long call or two hour long call the
likelihood that those words are gonna
appear is quite high
that's really say anything because in
two hours many words are going to be
spoken exactly right and you might think
that the longer the phone call is the
less you know as time goes on it's less
likely that they're that they're getting
what they want
yeah so so one of the things that we had
to figure out which was actually kind of
fun I didn't realize this is what I was
doing until I had the answer I was I was
thinking about it it's like how to tune
the model and then at once I had that
number I realized that what we've done
is we measured the efficiency of phone
calls and it turns out that if you if
you're on a call to a business and you
spend twice as long on the phone you get
about six sixty percent more done and so
you have you have diminishing returns
and so I find that interesting you know
if you if you have three things that you
need to get done on the phone
you're better off calling twice you know
just call once KQ of end of the call
things actually show you're analyzing
things that are also interesting for
people that call a call center rather
than front of people that work at a call
center yeah we're not uh we're not
selling that as a service at the moment
but we could coach you on how to how to
better businesses so do you have any
other things that are that go wrong what
else is very hard about this voice
analysis that people I'm also thinking
of the next topic I want to ask you
about if our listeners also want to do
this type of analysis themselves what
are definitely pitfalls that people
should watch out for yeah so I think it
depends on whether they're interested in
doing the speech-to-text part where
they're actually analyzing the audio
stream and turning that into text or
whether they want to do the stuff that I
work on which is extracting meaning from
the text they definitely have different
pitfalls the speech-to-text is those are
quite complicated algorithms so I don't
know how easy it would be to try to
write one from scratch but there are new
open source projects that that provide
frameworks for designing these types of
models and playing around with it could
you give an example of some of those
open source projects that people might
want to check out
they do this we shoot text yeah so so
one really neat one is called
call dia it's que al di and it said it
looks like it's a framework for
designing these types of models and so
they provide different implementations
of those algorithms like we talked about
at the beginning of the episode to do
speech to text you have to chain
together multiple different
probabilities there's a connection
between the acoustic signature and
phoneme and then phonemes words and then
words based on the context and so they
they provide a framework where you can
try out different implementations of
these things and chain them together and
try to make your own model and then you
know the more modern like as of the last
couple of years approach is to rather
than designing something based on these
linguistic models to try to use a deep
neural network to sort of fit all of
those probabilistic connections in one
go and Mozilla has an open-source
implementation of one of those neural
networks I've been meaning to try it for
months now and I haven't gotten to it
yet but I'm excited to do you know the
name of that open-source framework I
think it's called deep speech speech
okay we can always look it up later and
make sure it in the show notes for
people to use yes yeah I think I've been
meaning to try it out of it what's
really interesting yeah that will be
you're quite a different approach from
the things you were doing now because
it's neural networks rather than let's
say classical humor yeah you know I
suspect that it's fundamentally doing
the same things but rather than having a
linguistic expert divide the process
into different chunks and you train
separate models for each chunk I think
the idea here is to design a
architecture for the neural network that
can do those that same series of tasks
but it learns them all simultaneously
and so you have some subtype of
classifier that can look at that
acoustic signature and map it to
phonemes and then rather than a hidden
Markov model
to model the sequence of phonemes and
the transitions between them you use a
recurrent neural network for that I
think it's a similar idea fundamentally
just a totally different way of training
it and and interacting with the data
okay so if I hear your talk about all
those algorithms you say stuff like
Markov models and deep neural Nets so
suppose people in in our audience wanna
also get started with these algorithms
and these open source frameworks what
basics do you really need to know to
work on this is it easy enough that you
could just use something like that
mozilla framework even though you don't
really understand all the deep
algorithms or do you really need to know
some basics one neat things about these
types of probabilistic models is they're
often framed as generative models and so
it said it's a style of model duh when
you design it you imagine you're
designing something that could generate
the data and then essentially you fiddle
with the parameters in the model such
that the types of data that it would
generate look like the data that you
have and that that process you don't
amazingly you don't need to totally
understand the internals of the model in
in the case of a neural network you need
to be able to take a derivative of the
model output with respect to the
parameters and new software libraries
like tensor flow they do those
derivatives automatically and so one of
the really neat things about deep neural
networks and deep learning today is
tensorflow is really allowed for a huge
burst of creativity in designing these
types of models because you don't you
don't need to understand all of the
internals and you don't need to code
everything up explicitly you can have
this architecture and you can think
about it at a really high level and then
tensorflow sort of does the math for you
so I find that fascinating
nice yeah so so there there isn't
something you should specifically know
or learn you can actually just get
started but what would be some of the
some of the pitfalls something you and
your expensive experience working with
these types of algorithms what are
things we should have or be careful of
do you need do you need training data do
you need cool
that are longer than such-and-such what
are some things that would be
requirements you would say when is this
going to be a good technology to try out
first speech to text I you need a lot of
data and I think that's one of the real
struggles with us for the stuff that I
work on which is extracting meaning from
the text that I think is a much easier
type of analysis to dive into on your
own
perhaps prejudiced because that's what I
do but I actually believe that and I
think there's a huge range of levels of
analysis you can do from very simple to
very to very complicated I think what I
found really interesting and what I
think is one of the big mistakes that a
lot of people make when analyzing
language is that they don't seriously
consider the statistics of language and
word choice and so a lot of
off-the-shelf machine learning levels
they implicitly assume that things
follow normal distributions and snow not
always explicitly laid out in the model
but it it seems to be an implicit
assumption into a lot of them and word
choices is really not not normally
distributed so there's a lot of
interesting patterns in in language one
of them that I find amazing it's called
as if law what is that yeah it's named
for zipzee IPF and he was a linguist I
think 200 years ago and he started he
started looking through I think
encyclopedia and he looked at he tallied
up how often every word appeared and
just counted you know how often every
word appeared they found that the most
common word in English was duh and Buzz
which makes sense and that's the second
most common word I don't remember what
it is
but the important thing is the second
most common word appears half as often
as the most common word and the third
most common what's common word appears a
third is often is amiss common word and
the tenth most common word appears a
tenth as often is the most common word
and so the the word choice follows that
kind of pattern that's called a power
law and it's not at all like a normal
just
and it's a totally different
mathematical function and what I think
is just magical about this first of all
we don't know why we're choice would
follow that distribution it's a very
particular function but it seems to be
true what's really neat is it was
discovered for English but people have
since repeated the analysis for Spanish
and for Dutch and for German and all
kinds of dozens of different languages
and they all have this property and so
there seems to be something fundamental
about human language that has this
property and a lot of the natural
language processing models don't don't
take advantage of this fact so I find
that really interesting yeah and it's
really good to know because you might
want to apply algorithms where you think
the normal distribution would fit and
then it doesn't because it's the zip-zip
slothful what's the name again that's
really good to know you have any other
of those specific things like here's
some things that are really nice to know
if you want to use these algorithms yeah
another really important one is that
again a lot of machine learning models
assume conditional independence and so
they assume that your probability of
using a word might depend either it
doesn't depend on context at all or it
depends on a context of a few words
surrounding it but there's another
phenomenon in language called burstiness
which is that if you say it word once
you're more likely to say it again and
so you know we have a huge number of
synonyms there you might have 10 words
that you could choose from to express an
idea and the first time that you make
your selection that might be random but
then once you've explained something
that way you're gonna keep using the
same explanation again and then if we're
having a conversation and you explain
something one way I'm actually likely to
pick up on your word choice and repeat
it and so there's kind of a rich get
richer phenomenon in word choice where
once you start using a word it become
you use it more and then you use it even
more and that also leads to something
that's not normally distributed you know
some words get all of the usage and some
get almost none but then in a different
conversation those might trade roles and
so there's really real
some interesting statistics underlying
all these things but that's the part
that I find really interesting yes it's
a combination of knowing a little bit
about machine learning models like
knowing the difference between
supervised and unsupervised and do you
want to use a neural nets or nodes and
also some specific knowledge or natural
language processing like how often words
occur and how speech patterns with
people in general work so it's exactly
at the intersection of those two domains
where you at least need a little bit of
knowledge before you can apply this just
enough knowledge to be dangerous I find
it really fun that cycle where you you
think about a phenomenon that you want
to model and then you have to think
about okay well how can i implement this
in code and you know translating between
those ideas and the code I find out to
be really recording and this is also of
course a matter of understanding from
what situation what algorithm what type
of machine learning model would make
most sense how do you distinguish
between one situation what
characteristics choose a situation have
where you say this fits more a
supervised machine learning more and
more in a supervisory learning or more
on neural nets can you help us decide if
we have this plethora of options of
different algorithms what type of
situations which would be most useful
well so typically it depends on the task
that I want to solve so I think about I
think about the features that are
important for me so if I'm doing
classification for instance and I'm
looking for words and phrases that
indicate that something happened on a
call and then I will typically try to
figure out what is the absolute simplest
model that I could do the the simplest
dumbest thing I could do that would have
the the minimum needed to accomplish
this task and then I implement that and
I see how well it works and then I try
to beat that and often that's really
hard to hoon
so I would say start you know start
simple and get something working and
then you can see where it succeeds and
where it fails and and try to understand
what's leading to those failures and
then see if you can accommodate job into
the model but I think that the key for
me is to always have that baseline to
compare to because it's really easy for
me to come up with all these ideas and
say yeah I'm gonna fit for this and this
and accommodate for this and you know I
can have these wonderful ideas but
sometimes it doesn't do any better than
the simple model so I think what you're
saying is it is a little bit hard to
know upfront you should just try to
start small and start simple and then
iterate from where you are then yeah
yeah at least that's that's the approach
that I take I and I find that you know
it's easiest to do with you if you have
a problem that you're really interested
in so the the first text analysis thing
that I worked on was about looking at
authorship issues and trying to figure
out who wrote a given document there's a
historical puzzle dating from the early
days of the United States they're a set
of documents called the Federalist
Papers and they were written anonymously
at the time but we now know that they
were written by Alexander Hamilton and
James Madison went on to become early
presidents of the country and some of
the papers we know were written by
Hamilton and some of them we know were
written by Madison and then there's
about a third of the papers that are
that have been disputed and so over the
years there have been a number of people
who've tried to you know definitively
say who wrote which ones and for the
most part those different analyses have
not agreed so when I was first getting
into machine learning and doing my
career switch from astrophysics into
today to science I came across that
problem that I thought well this would
be really fun to see you know if I can
design a statistical model based on on
word choice and word usage to try to
make this determination so that was kind
of my entree into this field
and I had a problem that I was really
interested in and I really wanted to
know the answer and I wanted to see how
well I could do on this and again I
started simple and and started trying to
make these predictions and comparing
them with what different historians and
said earlier and did you find anything
new would your algorithm that historians
didn't find my conclusion was that
Madison had written almost all of the
disputed ones so historians have gone in
cycles were over some periods they think
Hamilton wrote most of them and some
periods they think Madison wrote most of
them and so on so their tenth there tend
to be these waves so my analysis agreed
with the Madison Nights interesting and
we will probably never know exactly so
who know because well of course I'm on
that no dad actually was everything I
wanted to ask you is there anything you
wanted to share before we close the
interview nice so one more question we
always ask our guest is where can we
read more about you about your company
about the work you do do you have any
links for US food in show notes yes the
company is in VOCA I and V OCA
and we have a company blog and then our
engineering team for software engineers
and data scientists we also have a
technical blog nice we'll make sure that
we add the links of all of those blogs
to the show now so people can check it
out and learn more about what you do and
how you use the Voisin analysis
algorithms to do so thanks so much for
being on the show might thank you very
much thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by
your police software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack channel at SC radio.com you
can also email us at team @ SC - radio
net this and all other episodes of SU
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening